Welcome back to the advanced course on Tablo and the previous tutorial we created these a beautiful
four box plots.
And today we're going to learn how to analyze them.
We've got quite a lot of ground to cover so let's jump straight into it.
First off I'd like to make sure that everybody is on the same page and therefore let's look at how exactly
box plots work.
So I'm going to bring up a slide that I've prepared very excited about this.
All right.
So let's say you have an access as it can be vertical horizontal in all cases vertical so let's stick
with that and you have a certain number of observations that you can plot on this axis.
So there are 10 observations.
Now in order to create an a box plot which you have to do is you have to physically count the number
of observations of one two three up to 10 and then take the middle between them.
So in our case there's an even number of observations so there is no one middle observation.
The middle ones are 5 and six.
So we are going to put a line exactly between Fifth the fifth and the sixth observation.
Now what are we going to do is we're going to do the same thing for the top five here.
We've counted.
We have five observations.
The middle one is number three.
We put a line through that one.
Now those are the exact same thing for the bottom half.
One two three for five.
This is the middle one over here.
So we put a line through it.
Now if we replace these lines with a box we are slowly starting to create a box plot.
Now all we have to do is plot the whiskers so the whisker goes all the way up to the top one over here
and the other whisker goes all the way up to the bottom one here and elements of the book's plot have
their own names.
This is the minimum.
This is the first quartile or the lower quartile.
This is the median.
This is the upper quartile of the third quarter.
And this is the maximum.
And just make sure you don't get confused here.
This is not the mean this is the median and that's because of the way we've constructed it.
So that is how a box plot gets built.
So basically it's about counting the number of records and breaking it up into four Court-House So every
single Courtown has an equal number of records in it.
Now let's look at another example here again another axis.
We've got our observations and let's do the same thing.
So that's our median that is going to be our first quartile.
That is our third quartile.
Now if we connect them that's our box.
And now what we can do here is if we measure the distance between the third quarter and the first quarter
it is called the entire quartal range.
Well the way we can sort box plots is we want to make sure that our analysis is not affected by outliers
.
So if any observation falls too far away then we want to exclude it from the construction of boxwood
And how do we determine if an observation is too far away.
Well you need to take one and a half times the entire quarter mile range.
And that is going to be a cutoff point.
So if an observation falls further than that then you shouldn't include it in the box.
And it's considered an outlier.
So in this case our box flight is going to look like this and that Separ or out there is considered
to be an outlier.
All right so that's how books plus are constructed.
Now let's have a look at a few sample use cases of box plots.
So here I've got a horizontal axis and for a change we're going to be looking at horizontal box plots
and to make things interesting let's say we're analyzing sales representatives and their daily sales
.
So what would you rather would you rather have your observations plotted like this or would you rather
have your observations planned like this.
In both cases the median is the same.
It is a thousand dollars.
Now this is where we can look at the book's plot and if we create the box put for the first example
you will see that it is quite compact like that.
The second box plot is much more wider.
So what does that tell us that tells us that the variance in the first box plot is lower so you have
more chances of being closer to the median.
You can only from the observation that we have you are only going to be somewhere between these two
whiskers and more likely you're actually going to be inside the second and third quarter owls groups
and therefore you're more likely to be next to the median here.
You have more room to go up what you have more room to go down so that basically means that the risk
is higher or the volatility is higher and your sales reps can bring.
They do bring a median back over a thousand dollars per day but at the same time it can it can really
vary it can be anywhere on the right and you're on the left so you have more certainty from more compact
box what you have less certainty with a wider box.
Even given the same media and the way to think about it or another way to think about it is in terms
of distribution so this distribution is narrower this distribution is wider so if we talk in terms of
standard deviations instantiation is here is which is also a measure of variance.
Right.
So here the standard deviation is higher or larger here it's smaller so you have a more narrow distribution
and you're more likely to actually hit the nail on the head here.
Whereas here you can either go left or right which is more uncertain.
OK let's have a look at another example.
Can you tell me right away what do you think.
Is this a good box or a bad box point.
Let's say we're also measuring sales and now it's a vertical axis and of course would be better if it
were compacter like this but is this a good box or a bad spot.
And given that the minimum or the maximum are fixed and in essence the question we're asking is is this
box a lot better than this box plot.
And if you think of it in terms of median the median here is higher than the median here and it makes
the answer obvious of course.
This box Plaut is preferrable to this box.
So basically if if your media minimum and maximum fixed you want your box the pot or the box part of
the box what you want it to be as a higher or as closer as more closer to your desired result as possible
so here we're talking about sales so the larger sales or higher sales are better.
So we want the box to be higher not lower.
But that is the obvious answer.
How do how do we think of it in terms of distributions and how do we think of it exactly why this is
the case so if we plot them now sideways so this is the good box plot.
This is the bad box blood let's plot the observations that make these booklets happen.
So these are 10 observations in this case and these are 10 observations in this case.
How do we see them in terms of distributions.
And for me personally this is the part that drives this point home.
This is what makes things click.
So I'm going to put distributions here and this here you can see that this is a Arite skewed distribution
.
And by the way right skewed is because the tails on the right not we don't look at the hump.
We look at the tail where the tail is and that is how we define whether it's a right skewed or electrocuted
.
So this is a rice distribution and if you think of it in this sense what it's telling us is that if
you throw a random observation.
Another one observation onto this chart then it is more likely to end up in this area in this more dense
area than it is on in this tale part right because that's how distributions work.
There are more observations here so you've got your mean median mode in this part of the chart.
And this part of the chart so you throw a Aranda bearable here.
It is more likely to end up here and here and on this other side if you throw a random variable into
this environment into this example then what will happen is it will more likely end up on the right
side.
So this is a left skewed distribution that tells on the left but most of the observations are concentrated
over here so if you throw another round variable it will most likely end up here.
And which is good for us because the sales are higher so that is how I personally think of books plus
sometimes because you know we like distribution's we're used to them and they've got a lot of mathematics
behind them.
They got sand and things like that.
Bookstores are also also great but they're simpler things I think.
And when you think of them in terms of distributions it makes a lot of sense that why a box plot which
is which looks like this is worse.
If you want to be on the right of access then a box plot that looks like that.
OK.
So that is how box plots work.
Let's not jump back into Tablo and see what analysis we can derive from them there.
All right so there is our chart.
What can we see from this chart.
Knowing that everything we know now.
Well right away we can see outliers here and here.
So what this means is that in these three states in New South Wales Queensland and Victoria there are
companies that are underperforming in terms of the overall performance in that specific state.
Then in Queensland they are companies that are over performing.
Also if you put your mouse over the box plus you will get some information which directly relates to
the five points we discussed about box pots.
So the minimum the lower cost tell the medium the upper quartile and the maximum.
And if you use this information you can compare the box plots among each other and for instance we can
say that this box plot has the highest median which is 8 percent.
This one is also 8 percent but you can visually see that it's lower than this box part comes in a third
so the state has the third median which is 6 percent and this one has a 4 percent.
And finally let's talk about the variance and the sizes of the box plus you can see that this box plot
here and this box plot here they are pretty big compared to these two box plots.
And that means that the variance here is much greater so there is less certainty that the like a random
company thrown into this one of these states will be performing at the median net profit margin.
And bear in mind when we say random company we're not taking into account all the amazing things about
our specific company we're not taking into account the product differentiation that we can offer the
amazing customer service that we deliver and all those great things we were just saying if we throw
in a random company that performs comparable to the companies in that specific state and you know it's
work it's performing about a somewhere on average Wi-Fi on a certain level variance.
Where will it end up.
So it is likely to end up in this box but because the box is so big there is more uncertainty as to
where it will be performing in this specific state.
So basically we're kind of assessing the business environment in each of these states in Western Australia
once again there is more uncertainty where your company will end up in terms of net profit margin because
the bookstore is quite large here the box plus are smaller.
And as you remember what we just discussed which one is better let's say here would you rather have
this box here or would you have it up at the top you would rather have it up at the top because higher
profit net profit margin is better for us so this is not the best set up in this specific said could
have been better if this box had had been higher at the top would have been better.
On the other hand in Victoria you can see that the box part of the box part is at the top meaning that
the set up in this business environment is actually pretty good.
You can see that the box part is quite compact meaning that there is less uncertainty in terms of where
a random company would end up in terms of net profit margin.
And also you can see that the median of course the median is higher than these two other states but
also you can see that the box part of the box part is closer to where we want to be to the top.
And as we discussed that's a good thing as better than if this box part was lower.
So there we go that's how you analyze box plots and what can we conclude from here.
Well we can say that out of these three states you know since we already are working in or the businesses
operating in yourself wells out of these three states it's obvious that this state of Victoria is the
better one in terms of expansion in terms of a business environment and this analysis has been performed
based on competitor research.
Now that's not the end of our challenge.
We of course have to analyze the economies of these states.
We have to analyze how the industries are performing and how the populations are growing things like
that.
So we will definitely get to that.
This was like the very first stage and what we want to do now is when to use the rest of our analysis
and hopefully back this finding that the business environment seems to be best for this specific industry
at this specific time in Victoria.
And I look for the next Tauriel.
Until then happy on lising